# Veith Weilnhammer

CV



#### Personal Statement

I am a board-certified psychiatrist, psychotherapist, and computational neuroscientist. The central problem I want to understand is how conscious experiences are represented in the brain, and how changes in these representations lead to psychotic symptoms such as hallucinations or delusions.

## Education and Degrees

- 2023 **Habilitation degree in Experimental Psychiatry**, Charité, Berlin, Germany. The construction of unambiguous conscious experiences from ambiguous sensory information.
- 2023 Board certificate in Psychiatry & Psychotherapy.
- 2015 **Doctoral degree (MD)**, Charité, Berlin, Germany.

  Frontoparietal cortex mediates perceptual transitions in bistable perception (summa cum laude).
- 2015 Medical degree, Charité, Berlin, Germany.
- 2007-2015 Medical school, Charité, Berlin, Germany, and Universidade Nova, Lisbon, Portugal.
- 2006-2007 **Studium Generale**, Eberhard Karls Universität, Tübingen, Germany.

## Professional Experience

- 2023–present **Postdoctoral researcher**, Advisors: Doris Tsao, David Whitney, Helen Wills Neuroscience Institute, University of California, Berkeley, USA.
  - $Hall ucinations \ in \ biological \ and \ artificial \ neural \ networks \mid Digital \ mental \ health$
  - 2015–2023 **Postdoctoral researcher**, Advisor: Philipp Sterzer, Department of Psychiatry, Charité, Berlin, Germany. Visual perception | Neural correlates of consciousness | Neurobiology of schizophrenia
  - 2016–2023 **Psychotherapist in training**, Center for Psychotherapy, Humboldt Universität, Berlin, Germany. Cognitive behavioral therapy | Systemic psychotherapy
  - 2015–2023 **Resident psychiatrist**, Department of Psychiatry, Charité, Berlin, Germany.

    Inpatient unit for psychotic and affective disorders | Liaison psychiatry | Outpatients treatment center for addiction
  - 2012–2013 **Minerva fellow**, Advisor: Rafi Malach, Weizmann Institute, Rehovot, Israel. Neural correlates of consciousness

## Fellowships and Awards

- 2024-present NARSAD Young Investigator Award, Brain & Behavior Research Foundation, New York, USA.
- 2023-present Leopoldina Postdoctoral Fellowship, German National Academy of Sciences, Halle (Saale), Germany.
  - 2023 Walter Benjamin Fellowship (declined), DFG, Bonn, Germany.
  - 2019–2022 Clinician Scientist Fellowship, Berlin Institute of Health, Berlin, Germany.
  - 2017–2018 Junior Clinician Scientist Fellowship, Berlin Institute of Health, Berlin, Germany.
    - 2013 Minerva Short Term Fellowship, Minerva Foundation, Max-Planck Society, Munich, Germany.
  - 2007–2015 University Scholarship, German Academic Scholarship Foundation, Berlin, Germany.

#### Skills

- Clinical Ketamine-and TMS-assisted treatments, psychotherapy in schizophrenia and addiction.
- Experimental Psychophysics, computational modeling, machine learning, fMRI, TMS, EEG.

Code Python, R, Matlab.

Languages German, English, French, Portuguese, Spanish.

## Key Publications

- **Veith Weilnhammer**, Yuki Murai, and David Whitney. Dynamic predictive templates in perception. *Current Biology*, volume 0, August 2024.
- **Veith Weilnhammer**, Heiner Stuke, Kai Standvoss, and Philipp Sterzer. Sensory processing in humans and mice fluctuates between external and internal modes. *PLOS Biology*, volume 21, page e3002410, August 2023.
- Veith Weilnhammer, Merve Fritsch, Meera Chikermane, Anna-Lena Eckert, Katharina Kanthak, Heiner Stuke, Jakob Kaminski, and Philipp Sterzer. An active role of inferior frontal cortex in conscious experience. *Current Biology*, volume 31, pages 2868–2880.e8, July 2021.
- 2020 **Veith Weilnhammer**, Lukas Röd, Anna-Lena Eckert, Heiner Stuke, Andreas Heinz, and Philipp Sterzer. Psychotic Experiences in Schizophrenia and Sensitivity to Sensory Evidence. *Schizophrenia bulletin*, volume 46, pages 927–936, February 2020.
- 2018 **Veith Weilnhammer**, Heiner Stuke, Philipp Sterzer, and Katharina Schmack. The Neural Correlates of Hierarchical Predictions for Perceptual Decisions. *The Journal of Neuroscience*, volume 38, pages 5008–5021, May 2018.

#### All publications

- Veith Weilnhammer, Marcus Rothkirch, Deniz Yilmaz, Merve Fritsch, Lena Esther Ptasczynski, Katrin Reichenbach, Lukas Roediger, Philip Corlett, and Philipp Sterzer. N-Methyl-D-aspartate receptor hypofunction causes recurrent and transient failures of perceptual inference. *bioRxiv*, May 2024. Under Revision in Brain.
- **Veith Weilnhammer**, Yuki Murai, and David Whitney. Dynamic predictive templates in perception. *Current Biology*, volume 0, August 2024.
- **Veith Weilnhammer**. Where is the ghost in the shell? *Neuroscience of Consciousness*, volume 2024, page niae015, January 2024.
- 2024 Katrin Reichenbach, Marcus Rothkirch, Lucca Jaeckel, Philipp Sterzer, and **Veith Weilnhammer**. Anterior insular activity signals perceptual conflicts induced by temporal and spatial context. *bioRxiv*, 2024.
- 2024 Merve Fritsch, Jochen Michely, Lucca Jaeckel, Ida Rangus, Christoph Riegler, Jan Scheitz, Christian H. Nolte, Philipp Sterzer, and **Veith Weilnhammer**. Ischemic lesions to inferior frontal cortex alter the dynamics of conscious visual perception. *bioRxiv*, 2024.
- **Veith Weilnhammer**, Heiner Stuke, Kai Standvoss, and Philipp Sterzer. Sensory processing in humans and mice fluctuates between external and internal modes. *PLOS Biology*, volume 21, page e3002410, August 2023.
- 2023 Heiner Stuke, Kathlen Priebe, **Veith Weilnhammer**, Hannes Stuke, and Nikola Schoofs. Sparse models for predicting psychosocial impairments in patients with PTSD: An empirical Bayes approach. *Psychological Trauma: Theory, Research, Practice and Policy*, volume 15, pages 80–87, January 2023.
- 2023 Laurie-Anne Sapey-Triomphe, Lauren Pattyn, Veith Weilnhammer, Philipp Sterzer, and Johan Wagemans. Neural correlates of hierarchical predictive processes in autistic adults. Nature Communications, volume 14, page 3640, June 2023.
- 2023 Merve Fritsch, **Veith Weilnhammer**, Paul Thiele, Andreas Heinz, and Philipp Sterzer. Sensory and environmental uncertainty in perceptual decision-making. *iScience*, volume 26, page 106412, April 2023.
- 2022 Laurie-Anne Sapey-Triomphe, **Veith Weilnhammer**, and Johan Wagemans. Associative learning under uncertainty in adults with autism: Intact learning of the cue-outcome contingency, but slower updating of priors. *Autism: The International Journal of Research and Practice*, volume 26, pages 1216–1228, July 2022.

- 2022 Stephan Köhler, **Veith Weilnhammer**, Henrik Walter, Susanne Erk, Philipp Sterzer, and Anne Guhn. Autobiographical Script-Driven Imagery Has No Detectable Effect on Emotion Regulation in Healthy Individuals. *Neuropsychobiology*, volume 81, pages 141–148, 2022.
- 2021 **Veith Weilnhammer**, Merve Fritsch, Meera Chikermane, Anna-Lena Eckert, Katharina Kanthak, Heiner Stuke, Jakob Kaminski, and Philipp Sterzer. An active role of inferior frontal cortex in conscious experience. *Current Biology*, volume 31, pages 2868–2880.e8, July 2021.
- **Veith Weilnhammer**, Meera Chikermane, and Philipp Sterzer. Bistable perception alternates between internal and external modes of sensory processing. *iScience*, volume 24, page 102234, March 2021.
- 2021 Heiner Stuke, Elisabeth Kress, **Veith Weilnhammer**, Philipp Sterzer, and Katharina Schmack. Overly strong priors for socially meaningful visual signals are linked to psychosis proneness in healthy individuals. *Frontiers in psychology*, volume 12, page 583637, 2021.
- 2020 **Veith Weilnhammer**, Lukas Röd, Anna-Lena Eckert, Heiner Stuke, Andreas Heinz, and Philipp Sterzer. Psychotic Experiences in Schizophrenia and Sensitivity to Sensory Evidence. *Schizophrenia bulletin*, volume 46, pages 927–936, February 2020.
- 2018 **Veith Weilnhammer**, Heiner Stuke, Philipp Sterzer, and Katharina Schmack. The Neural Correlates of Hierarchical Predictions for Perceptual Decisions. *The Journal of Neuroscience*, volume 38, pages 5008–5021, May 2018.
- 2018 Heiner Stuke, **Veith Weilnhammer**, Philipp Sterzer, and Katharina Schmack. Delusion Proneness is Linked to a Reduced Usage of Prior Beliefs in Perceptual Decisions. *Schizophrenia Bulletin*, volume 45, pages 80–86, January 2018.
- 2017 Veith Weilnhammer, Heiner Stuke, Guido Hesselmann, Philipp Sterzer, and Katharina Schmack. A predictive coding account of bistable perception a model-based fMRI study. PLOS Computational Biology, volume 13, page e1005536, May 2017.
- 2017 Heiner Stuke, Hannes Stuke, **Veith Weilnhammer**, and Katharina Schmack. Psychotic Experiences and Overhasty Inferences Are Related to Maladaptive Learning. *PLOS Computational Biology*, volume 13, page e1005328, January 2017.
- Veith Weilnhammer, Philipp Sterzer, and Guido Hesselmann. Perceptual Stability of the Lissajous Figure Is Modulated by the Speed of Illusory Rotation. *PloS one*, volume 11, page e0160772, 2016.
- 2016 Katharina Schmack, **Veith Weilnhammer**, Jakob Heinzle, Klaas E Stephan, and Philipp Sterzer. Learning What to See in a Changing World. *Frontiers in human neuroscience*, volume 10, page 263, 2016.
- **Veith Weilnhammer**, Karin Ludwig, Philipp Sterzer, and G Hesselmann. Revisiting the Lissajous figure as a tool to study bistable perception. *Vision research*, volume 98, pages 107–12, May 2014.
- 2013 **Veith Weilnhammer**, Karin Ludwig, Guido Hesselmann, and Philipp Sterzer. Frontoparietal cortex mediates perceptual transitions in bistable perception. *The Journal of Neuroscience*, volume 33, pages 16009–15, October 2013.

# Individual Research Support

Ongoing

- 2024–present **Adversarial attacks on the human visual system**, Principle Investigator, Brain & Behavior Research Foundation, €38,000.
- 2023–present Hallucinations in biological and artificial neural networks., Principle Investigator, Leopoldina National Academy of Sciences, €100,800.

Completed

- 2019–2022 **The effect of prefrontal lesions on conscious experience**, Clinican Scientist, Berlin Institute of Health, €151,200.
- 2017–2018 **The influence of prior knowledge on perception in schizophrenia**, Junior Clinician Scientist, Berlin Institute of Health, €95,600.
  - 2013 **Dynamic causal modeling of intracranial EEG**, Investigator, Minerva-Foundation, €5,200.

_	- 1		
- 1	eacl	hır	١ø
•	Cuci		. ~

2021 -	2022	Sei	minar:	Cognit	ive	Functions	of the	Fronta	I Cortex
0010	0000		_	_					

2018 - 2022 Lecture: Computational Models of Schizophrenia

2018 - 2022 Online lecture: Schizophrenia as a Model Disorder

2016 - 2020 Seminar: Problem-Based Learning

2015 - 2022 **Bedside Teaching**: Biopsychosocial History and Psychopathology, mood disorders, adjustment disorders,

psychotic disorders, cognitive disorders, liaison psychiatry

2015 - 2017 **Seminar**: Mental Representations

## Higher Education Teaching Certifications

2022 Online teaching

2015 Problem-based learning

#### Mentorship

2023-present Supervision of undergraduate research project, Jasmine Lopez, University of California, Berkeley.

2020-present Co-supervision of MD thesis, Katrin Reichenbach, Charité, Berlin.

2019 Co-supervision of Master thesis, Deniz Yilmaz, Berlin School of Mind and Brain, Berlin.

2019 Supervision of Master thesis, Meera Chikermane, NeuroCure, Berlin.

2018–2022 Co-supervision of PhD thesis, Anna-Lena Eckert, Berlin School of Mind and Brain.

2018–2019 Co-supervision of Master thesis, Drew Cooper, NeuroCure, Berlin.

2018–2019 Co-supervision of Master thesis, Lukas Röd, Berlin School of Mind and Brain.

2017-present **Co-supervision of postdoctoral research project**, Merve Fritsch, Charité, Berlin.

#### Memberships

2024-present Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness.

2015-present **Medical Association**, Berlin, Germany.

#### Academic Services

Reviews PLOS Computational Biology, Journal of Neuroscience, Neuroscience of Consciousness, Schizophrenia Bulletin, Journal of Vision.